What I heard about your punctuality was no exaggeration.
关于我听到的有关您守时的话 并没有夸张
Please. - Thank you, thank you.
- 给您  - 谢谢 谢谢
For you, Irena, this humble bouquet.
给您的 伊雷娜 这束朴素的小花
Please, come in. Do come in...
请进 请 请
No, don't take it off! No, no...
不 别脱鞋 不 不
Absolutely.
必须的
I must introduce you to Sabina. Sabinka!
我必须向您介绍萨宾娜 萨宾卡
Sabinka! This is my daughter, Sabina.
萨宾卡 这是我的女儿萨宾娜
Mr. Józef, the one about whom you've heard so many good things from me.
约瑟夫先生 你听我说过他那么多好话
You are too kind to me. And your daughter...
您对我太好了 而女儿
is as beautiful as a dream.
美得像梦一样
I shall allow myself once again to drink to the health of this house.
请允许我再次为这所房子的健康干杯
I know from your mother that you work in the field of culture.
我从您母亲那里得知 您从事文化工作
Yes, Sabinka works at a publishing house.
是的 萨宾卡在出版社工作
It's a difficult field, I imagine?
这是个困难的领域 想必
One could say that.
也可以这么说
I must confess, I have little time for reading.
我必须承认 我没什么时间阅读
Life is short, and there is so much to do.
生命短暂 而周围有这么多事情
But I have a deep respect for books.
但我对书籍怀有敬意
From my mother, who read a great deal.
源于我的母亲 她读了很多书
During the war, when I worked in the finance department, I can swear to you
战争期间我在财政部工作时 我可以向您发誓
that with the writer who started on the Belvedere schedule,
对于那位在贝尔韦德街开办书店的女作家
I spoke as gently as a child.
我跟她说话像对孩子一样温柔
She hadn't the slightest clue about accounting.
她对会计一丁点儿概念都没有
Now, what was her name?...
她叫什么来着
Zofia Nałkowska? - Of course.
- 索菲亚·纳乌科夫斯卡  - 当然
I just need a reminder. So many names in my head...
我只需要一点提醒 脑子里有这么多姓氏
And you... forgive my curiosity,
您 原谅我的好奇
do you represent a specific department?
代表某个具体的部门吗
Polish poetry.
波兰诗歌
Ah, you hit the nail on the head!
对 您说中了
Poetry...
诗歌
Much... one might say...
很多 可以说
Here’s what I thought. Perhaps you would stay with us, have dinner together...
我是这么想的 也许您留下来和我们一起吃晚饭
We are having such a lovely conversation. - Only if I am not taking up your time.
- 我们聊得这么好  - 只要我没占用您的时间
Nonsense, please.
瞧您说的 请便
Sabinka, tell us, which costume will you wear to the parade?
萨宾卡 说说阅兵式那天你会穿哪套制服
Alright.
好的
Put on Schumann? - No, no, not now.
- 放舒曼吗  - 不 不 现在不放
First, I'll serve something at the table.
我先拿点东西摆在桌上
Oh, perhaps you're hungry? - No, no. I'll eat when he leaves.
- 怎么 你饿了吗  - 不 不 他走了我再吃
Please, don't be shy.
别客气 请不要拘束
If I don't answer, I'll just get embarrassed, that's all.
如果我不回答 我会感到羞愧 仅此而已
Sixteen times eighteen? - Very easy.
- 16乘以18  - 很简单
Very easy. Two hundred eighty-eight.
很简单 288
Sabinka, you don't believe me, but I ask you not to pity me.
萨宾卡 您不相信我 而我请您不要怜悯我
Right. I'd prefer three-digit numbers. For example...
是的 我更倾向于三位数 例如
228 times 314.
228乘以314
Want to check?
您想检查一下吗
I believe you.
我相信您
I see you have a good eye for people, Sabinka,
我看得出您很懂人 萨宾卡
because in multiplication, I have no equal. And in division as well...
因为在乘法上没人比得过我 除法也是
Mr. Józef, I just don't know if you like jellied pork shanks?
约瑟夫先生 我只是不知道您是否喜欢肉冻猪蹄
And not just jellied ones, madam.
不只是肉冻的 尊敬的夫人
That's just how I am—I have an appetite.
我就是这样的 胃口很好
If the ladies permit... another half glass, because
如果女士们允许 再来半杯 因为
this cordial is fit for a king...
这露酒是极好的
Well, what do you think of that accountant?
那么 那个会计怎么样
Mom will tell you everything about him. - But... do you like him?
- 妈妈会告诉你关于他的一切  - 但是 你喜欢他吗
Mrs. Irena, you have a beautiful daughter
伊雷娜夫人 您的女儿很漂亮 而且极其聪明
and she is incredibly intelligent.
是的
Yes.
如果她愿意把我当作潜在的未婚夫来考虑
If she were to consider me as a potential fiancé,
请告诉她 我赚得不错 而且在外面也能赚点外快
please tell her that I earn a decent living, and I can earn extra on the side.
跟我在一起她一切都会充足
With me, she would have more than enough of everything. Only, you understand, I cannot tell her this myself.
只是 您明白 我不能亲自跟她说这话
But, Józef, I don't need to sing your praises.
但是 约瑟夫 不需要我来夸赞您
You present yourself perfectly well.
您已经把自己介绍得很出色了
Please, help yourself.
请随便吃
And don't look at me,
别管我
after one glass my blood pressure rises so much, I can't sleep at all.
我这人喝一杯后血压就会升高 根本没法睡觉
Goodness! Has something happened to you? - Nothing of the sort.
- 天哪 您怎么了  - 没什么
I scared you, didn't I? Scared you? I scared you!
我吓到您了 是吗 吓到了 吓到了